Finding Aid for University of Michigan News and Information Services Photographs, 1946-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan News and Information Services Photographs 1946-2006
University of Michigan News and Information Services Photographs.
87265 Bimu C475 2
Ten series of negatives, slides and copy prints documenting all aspects of University of Michigan life and activities, includes prints used in the University Record.
125.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan News and Information Services (donor no. 285 ) periodically deposits its photographs with the library.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
News and Information Services (NIS) is the media relations office of the University of Michigan. NIS disseminates (to internal and external audiences) information about university programs, research, and activities of faculty and staff, primarily through the news media. NIS also responds to media requests for information about the university. Staff is comprised of information officers and editors covering specific university units, a photography unit, and a radio and television unit. This office also publishes The University Record, a weekly newspaper for faculty and staff, and Michigan Today, a quarterly tabloid newspaper sent to U-M alumni (complete sets of these publications are held by the Bentley Library). Some units on campus handle media relations through offices largely independent of NIS. These units include sports information, the Medical Center, the College of Engineering, Law School, and Business School.
News and Information Services has undergone several name and organizational changes, but can trace its roots to 1897, when the Regents requested a plan for to disseminate University news to the State. This original department of information services was primarily responsible for publishing newsletters and frequently struggled to finance its operations. By 1930, the need for a news agency had grown, and following the installation of President Alexander G. Ruthven, the university created a News Dissemination Service (often called the University of Michigan News Service). Led by Wilfred B. Shaw, the Service had two primary functions. First, it was responsible for preparing weekly releases for nearly 800 newspapers throughout the state and beyond. This reporting included news about the Regents, research conducted by professors, affairs of the student body, and all other campus news with the exclusion of athletics. The second function was to send news about individual students to their home town papers. (Michigan Alumnus May 27, 1959).
Originally part of the Bureau of Alumni Relations, in 1942 the University News Service, now led by Donald K. Anderson, became an independent department. In 1946, Arthur L. Brandon was appointed as the Director of Information Services and took over responsibility for the public information services on behalf of the University, services which included the University News Service, news photography, and promotional publications. In 1948, services expanded with the acquisition of the WUOM radio station and continued to adapt to new media with the addition of television.
With the administrative changes resulting from the installment of President Harlan H. Hatcher, Brandon's title was changed to Director of University Relations and the University News Service became part of the Office of University Relations. Other changes followed, with Regents meetings being opened to the press in 1954 and University News Service taking on photographic coverage at athletic events in 1956. In 1957, Brandon resigned from his position and was replaced by Lyle M. Nelson. As Director of University Relations, Nelson combined radio and television under the director of broadcasting. Nelson retired in 1961 and was replaced by Michael Radock. One year later, administrative reorganization created an Information Service.
The Information Service consisted of three divisions, including News Service, News Photography, and Community Relations. Further reorganization in 1963 and 1964 moved the publications and editorial services under the umbrella of Information Services and saw the promotion of Cleland B. Wyllie, who had been with the News Service since the 1940s, to Director of Media Relations.
While the Office of University Relations underwent several changes and reorganizations in the following years, Information Services remained under its jurisdiction until 1998, when the office was divided into three vice presidential posts. One of these new posts was the Vice President for Media Relations, which was responsible for the University's News Service. In 2000, the Media Relations became the Office of the Vice President for Communications, which is where the current News Service resides in the University organization. News Service has continued to expand its media types and now includes podcasts, social media, and other online resources in addition to its print, radio, and television services.
Current information about News and Information Services and on-line versions of the University Record and Michigan Today (with searchable back issues of the Record from September 1992, and Michigan Today from December 1993) is available on the Web at the following URL: http://ns.umich.edu/new/.
The News and Information Services Photographs document many aspects of university and community life, particularly activities of the administration, faculty, departments, and students beginning in 1946 and continuing into the early 1980s. Photographs were, for the most part, made by the staff of the News Service (later Information Services and now News and Information Services) for use with university press releases, or upon request of individuals with the university, or for outside media with special interests in university personnel or activities.
The record group presently consists of 10 series (A-J).
The series are comprised primarily of black and white negatives and contact sheets, although Series E includes six linear feet and one oversize box of prints, most of which are 8" x 10" black and white images, and Series H includes color transparencies. There are also prints in Series I, Series J, slides in Series E and I, and a 16 mm film in Series I. Color negatives become more frequent in the late 1980s.
The original order and file headings created by News and Information Services have been retained wherever possible. Thus, the several lettered series reflect various organizational schemes used in the past.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Photographs.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. News and Information Services.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1981-1990.; University record.
- Series A circa 1946-1957
  Series A (12 linear ft.; ca. 1946-1956) consists of black and white 4" x 5" negatives and 2-1/4" x 2-1/4" negatives with occasional contact prints, produced from about 1946 to 1956. The negatives cover a broad range of university topics.
  This series is arranged into broad subjects with a chronological order within the subject headings. Building names have frequently been used for organizing the material rather than departmental names. Often included under the name of buildings are activities, departments, equipment, laboratories, machinery, offices, services, and individuals. For example, Bureau of Appointments may be found under Administration Building - Interior. Building names are those that were current when the photographs were made.
  There is a subject index (created by News and Information Services) to Series A in the inventory section of this finding aid.
  - A-D
    - Ackerman, R., see Francis, Dr. Thomas (Box A1)
    - Administration Building (old Administration Building now LSA), 10+ negatives
      - Accounting and Tabulating (Box A1)
      - Bureau of Appointments (Box A1)
      - General views (Box A1)
      - Payroll Office (Box A1)
      - Personnel Office (Box A1)
      - Purchasing Department (Box A1)
      - Regents Room (Box A1)
      - Student Affairs Office see also "President's Office" (Box A1)
        (see also Registrar's Office)
    - Administrative Officials (Box A1)
    - Aeronautical Engineering, see North Campus (Box A1)
    - Air Force, 10+ negatives (Box A1)
    - Air Show 2 (Box A1)
    - Albion College (Alumni, meeting of), 10+ negatives (Box A1)
    - Algood, Lee (Box A1)
    - Alumni, 10+ negatives (Box A1)
    - Association/Council (Box A1)
    - Fund (Box A1)
    - Memorial Hall (Box A1)
    - Reunion Luncheons (Baseball, Dental, Engineering, General, Literature, Medical) (Box A1)
    - American Alumni Council, 10+ negatives (Box A1)
    - American Association of University Women 7 (Box A1)
    - American College Public Relations Association (Box A1)
    - American Judiciary Society (Box A1)
    - American Society of Mechanical Engineers (Box A1)
    - Angell, Carleton, see Museums Building (Box A1)
    - Angell Hall, 10+ negatives (Box A1)
    - Ann Arbor, city of/Scenes, 4 negatives (Box A1)
    - Ann Arbor High School, 2 negatives (Box A1)
    - Ann Arbor News Press (Box A1)
    - Arab Student Conference 103 (Box A1)
    - Arboretum 2 (Box A1)
    - Architecture and Design, School of, 10+ negatives (Box A1)
    - Art-prints on loan, students 3 (Box A1)
    - Arts Chorale (Box A1)
    - Astronomical Society (heads of) (Box A1)
    - Astronomy (Box A1)
    - Athletics
      - Baseball (Box A1)
      - Basketball (Box A1)
      - Board in control of (Box A1)
      - Buildings (Box A1)
      - Cheerleaders (Box A1)
      - Football-arr. by year through 1956 (Box A1)
      - Football (Box A2)
      - Golf (Box A2)
      - Homecoming Swimming (Box A2)
      - Tennis (Box A2)
      - Track and Field (Box A2)
      - Weight Lifting (Box A2)
      - Wrestling (Box A2)
    - Audio Visual, 10 negatives approximate (Box A2)
    - Automotive Engineering (Laboratory, Society of), 7 negatives (Box A2)
    - Autoradiography (Box A2)
    - Band, American Band Masters Assoc. (Box A2)
    - Band, Kappa Kappa Psi initiation (Box A2)
    - Band, Marching, by year, 10+ negatives (Box A2)
    - Band, Symphony, 10+ negatives (Box A2)
    - Barbour Gym. (Box A2)
      (see Waterman Gym. see also Women's Physical Education)
    - Bartell, Prof. Floyd, testing aerbond (Box A2)
    - Bell, Dr. Margaret, see Women's Phys. Ed: Swimming (Box A2)
    - Bender, Mr. and Mrs. William (Box A2)
      (see Halloween Mask)
    - Biedermann, Les, see Traverse City (Box A2)
    - Biological Station, 10+ negatives (Box A2)
    - Biology, Dept. of (Box A2)
      (see also Natural Science Bldg.)
    - Blind, devices for (Box A2)
    - Blood bank/Blood drive, 4 negatives (Box A2)
    - Book Mobile (Box A2)
    - Botany, Dept. of, 10+ negatives (Box A2)
    - Boys, Prof. Richard (Box A2)
      (see Handy, W.C.)
    - Broadcasting, 10+ negatives (Box A2)
    - Brown, Gordon (Box A2)
      (see Francis, Dr. Thomas)
    - Brush Dynamo (Box A2)
      (see Engineering, School of)
    - Bureau of Government Library (Box A2)
    - Bureau of School Services, 2 negatives (Box A2)
    - Burton Tower, 10+ negatives (Box A2)
    - Business Administration, School of, 10+ negatives (Box A3)
    - Business Education, workshop on, 9 negatives (Box A3)
    - Business Research, Bureau of, 2 negatives (Box A3)
    - Buss, Waldo and Dr. Kerlikowske (Box A3)
    - Busses, University (Box A3)
    - C (Box A3)
    - Cadillac (Mich.) Medical Students, 2 negatives (Box A3)
    - Camp Davis (Geology) (Box A3)
    - Camp (Filibert) Roth, 10+ negatives (Box A3)
    - Campus Affairs Committee (Box A3)
    - Campus Policemen, 2 negatives (Box A3)
      (see UM Security Police)
    - Campus Scenes (Box A3)
      (see also individual campus buildings, Diag, President's house, fraternities, sororities, Student activities, Residence halls, Univ. schools and depts., North Campus, Homecoming, Honors Convocation, Language Laboratory, Orientation, Athletics, Men's and Women's Phys. Ed., Registration, Summer Session, Libraries)
    - Cardio-Vascular Research (Box A3)
    - Carpenter shop (Box A3)
    - Cemetery, military (Box A3)
    - Center for Continuing Education of Women (Box A3)
    - Center for Japanese Studies, 10+ negatives (Box A3)
    - Cheerleaders (Box A3)
      (see Athletics)
    - Chemistry/Pharmacy (Pharmacy, see also Medical (Box A3)
    - School, Pharmaceutical Lab), 10+ negatives (Box A3)
    - Chemistry Stores, 3 negatives (Box A3)
    - Christmas carolers, 2 negatives (Box A3)
    - Church, Mike and Fred Dustin (Box A3)
    - Churches, 10+ negatives (Box A3)
    - Citizen Conferences/Citizenship, 2 negatives (Box A3)
    - City Planners (Box A3)
    - Classroom scenes (Box A3)
      (see Student Activities)
    - Clements Library, 10+ negatives (Box A3)
    - Clingman, William and Jane (Box A3)
    - Coliseum (Box A3)
    - Commencement, 10+ negatives (Box A3)
    - Community Planning (Box A3)
    - Concrete, testing of (Box A3)
    - Conferences (arranged alphabetically
      - Accountants' (Box A4)
      - Actuarial Sciences' (Box A4)
      - Advertising (Box A4)
      - Asian-American (Box A4)
      - Band Directors' (Box A4)
      - Bankers' (Box A4)
      - Boy Scouts of America (Box A4)
      - City Managers' (Box A4)
        (see Institute of Public Administration)
      - Deans' (Box A4)
      - Economic Outlook (Box A4)
      - Education of Student life in U.S. (Box A4)
      - Education, Summer English Writers' Executive Development (Box A4)
      - Finance (Box A4)
      - Fire Instructors' Football Traffic Control (Box A4)
      - Foundry (Box A4)
      - Fuel Spray (Box A4)
      - Furniture Executives' (Box A4)
      - Hardward (Box A4)
      - Hospital Planning Management Market Research (Box A4)
      - Municipal Purch. Corp. (Box A4)
      - Musicology (Box A4)
      - National Band Conductors' (Box A4)
      - National Scholastic Press (Box A4)
      - Parent Education Pastors' (Box A4)
      - Principal/Freshmen Public Health (Box A4)
      - Radiological Health (Box A4)
      - School boards: Officials and Laymen (Box A4)
      - School masters' Steelman's Foundry (Box A4)
    - Cooley Building (Mortimer E.), 10+ negatives (Box A4)
    - Cooperative Housing, 4 negatives (Box A4)
    - Cork, Prof. James M (Box A4)
      (see also Physics, Cyclotron)
    - Corkery, William and Japanese wife (Box A4)
    - Correspondence Study Department (Box A4)
    - Counselling Services (Box A4)
      (see Freshman/Freshwomen)
    - Counselling lab-U. Elementary School (Box A4)
    - Counselors, Academic (Box A4)
    - Curriculum Planning Committee-LSA (Box A4)
    - Cuthbert, Ivan H.-Ext. Center (Box A4)
    - Cyclotron (Box A4)
      (see North campus)
    - Damon Runyan Research Fund Dean of Women (Bacon, Lloyd) (Box A4)
    - Debating Club, 2 negatives (Box A4)
    - Dennison, Prof. David M., 2 negatives (Box A4)
    - Dentistry, School of, 10+ negatives (Box A4)
    - Detroit Free Press Awards, 3 negatives (Box A4)
    - Detroit Times National Tournament of Orators (Box A4)
    - Development Council (Box A4)
    - Dietetics and Dieticians, 2 negatives (Box A4)
      (see also Hospital, Univ. Dietician)
    - Dines, Edith (Box A4)
      (see Kamrowski, Gerome)
    - Diplomas (Box A4)
    - Displaced Students (European) (Box A4)
    - Dorr, Professor Harold, 10+ negatives (Box A4)
      (includes Legislature filmstrip shots)
    - Drama Season/workshops, 10+ negatives (Box A4)
    - Driver Training, 8 negatives (Box A4)
    - Drum Majors (Box A4)
      (see Band, Marching)
    - Drummond, William H., Master Sgt. (Box A4)
    - Duey, Philip A. (Box A4)
    - Dufek, Donald (Box A4)
      (see Athletics/and Student Activities)
    - Dump, behind UM Hospital (Box A4)
    - Dustin, Fred (author on Gen. George A. Custer) (Box A4)
      (see also Church Mike)
  - E-H
    - East Hall, 2 negatives (Box A4)
    - East Quadrangle, 10+ negatives (Box A4)
      (, incl. EQ Radio Station)
    - Eberbach (Box A4)
    - Economics, School of, 4 negatives (Box A4)
    - Education, School of (Box A4)
    - University Elementary School, 10+ negatives (Box A4)
    - University High School, 7 negatives (Box A4)
      (see also Group Dynamics)
    - Employee activities (Box A4)
      (see University of Michigan, Employee Activities)
    - Engineering, School of (Box A4)
    - General. shots, incl. the Centennial (Box A4)
    - East Engineering Building (Box A4)
    - West Engineering Building (Box A4)
    - Engineering Research Institute, 10+ negatives (Box A4)
    - English Department, 3 negatives (Box A4)
    - English Language Dept./Institute, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Extension (Educational) Service, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
      (see also General Library and Television)
    - Faculty (a meeting, grading of by students), 2 negatives (Box A5)
    - Far Eastern Association (Box A5)
    - Far Eastern Languages and Literature (Box A5)
    - Fariss, Walter B., veterans coordinator (Box A5)
    - Fine Arts Dept., 2 negatives (Box A5)
      (see also Architecture and Design, school of)
    - Fipple flute (recorder) (see also Extension Service) (Box A5)
    - Fire College/Firemanship award, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Fiscal Situation of University 1949 (Box A5)
    - Fishing and Fisheries, Department of, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Fisheries Research, Institute for, 3 negatives (Box A5)
    - Fletcher Hall, 5 negatives (Box A5)
    - Flint College, 5 negatives (Box A5)
    - Flint Project-Social Science Seminar, 3 negatives (Box A5)
    - Food Service (including Building), 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Ford Scholarships, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Foreign Students (individuals), 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Forensic Association (Box A5)
    - Francis, Dr. Thomas with Dr. Gordon Brown and R. Ackerman, 2 negatives (Box A5)
    - Fraternities (listed alphabetically), 10+ negatives (Box A5)
      (see also Bard, Kappa Kappa Psi; initiation)
    - Fresh Air Camp, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Freshman View Book, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Freshmen/Freshwomen (include Counselling Services for) (Box A5)
    - Frieze Building (Box A5)
    - Galens-Medical Society-sales and collections, 2 negatives (Box A5)
    - Gallon, Jack, Mrs. Gallon and Prof. Smith (Box A5)
    - General Library (see also Extension Service), 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - General Services Building, 4 negatives (Box A5)
    - Geography Department, 2 negatives (Box A5)
    - Geography Camp (Box A5)
    - Geology (Box A5)
    - George, Edwin S., Reserve, 2 negatives (Box A5)
    - Gerontology (Box A5)
    - Gilbert and Sullivan Society (Box A5)
    - Gjelness, Ruth (Box A5)
    - Gordon Hall (Dexter Mansion), 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Grass Lake, visit by Prof. Whittemore, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Greathouse, Thomas (Box A5)
    - Great Lakes Research Institute, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Great Lakes Waterways Commission (Box A5)
    - Group Dynamics; Personnel, 7 negatives (Box A5)
    - Gulantics, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Gustafson, A.H. (Box A5)
    - Gustafson, Prof. Felix G. (Box A5)
    - Haas, Rosamond (Box A5)
    - Hackett, Arthur (Box A5)
    - Haines, Donal H. (Box A5)
    - Hale, Clayton (Box A5)
    - Halloween Mask (made by Mr. & Mrs. Wm. Bender) (Box A5)
    - Hamilton, Francis M. Memorial Fountain (Box A5)
      (see Plaques and Statuary)
    - Hamtramck, John F., tomb of (Box A5)
      (see Statues, Plaques and Monuments)
    - Handicapped Students (Box A5)
      (see Waterman Gymnasium and)
    - Handy, W.C., and Professor Richard C. Boys, 2 negatives (Box A5)
    - Hardy, William & Son (Box A5)
    - Harvey, James, playwright (Box A5)
    - Hatcher, Harlan H, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Hatcher (Harlan H.) Inauguration, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
      (see also Alumni Reunion and North Campus Groundbreaking)
    - Haven Elm (Box A5)
    - Haven Hall, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Hawley, Richard (Box A5)
    - Health Service, 10+ negatives (Box A5)
    - Haven Hall, 10+ negatives (Box A6)
    - Howley, Richard (Box A6)
    - Health Service, 10+ negatives (Box A6)
    - Hearst Oratorical Speech Winners (Box A6)
    - Hebrard, Professor Jean (Architecture) (Box A6)
    - Henize, Karl, 2 negatives (Box A6)
    - Hiawatha Club, Officers of (Box A6)
    - Highland Park High School-Future Librarians group (Box A6)
    - High School accrediting certificate (Box A6)
    - High School Students (Box A6)
      (see also Conferences: Principals and Freshmen, Education, School of, University High School, Highland Park High School, Future Librarians Group, Journalism Dept.: Michigan Interscholastic Press Assoc. Michigan Youth Symphony, Port Huron High School, Wolverine Girls' State)
    - Highway Camp (Box A6)
    - Hill Auditorium, 10+ negatives (Box A6)
    - Hinsdale, Ellen (Box A6)
    - Hobbs, Prof. William H.(geology) (Box A6)
    - Hochrein, Bessie (Box A6)
    - Hoisington, Robert H. (Engineering) (Box A6)
    - Holmquist, Barbara, pianist (Box A6)
    - Homecoming 10+ (Box A6)
    - Honors Convocation 10+ (Box A6)
    - Hopwood Awards, Speakers and Winners, 10+ negatives (Box A6)
    - Hopwood Room, 10+ negatives (Box A6)
    - Hospital, University, 10+ negatives
      - Alice Lloyd Radiation Center (Box A6)
      - Children's Psychiatric Hospital (Box A6)
      - Dermatology (Box A6)
      - Dieticians/Kitchen, see also Dietetics and Dieticians (Box A6)
      - Heart Station (see also Cardiovascular Research) Hematology/Blood Bank (Box A6)
      - Outpatient Clinic/Emergency Room (Box A6)
      - Pediatrics (Box A6)
      - Pharmacy (Box A6)
      - Physical Therapy Unit (Box A6)
      - Respirator Center/Polio Patients (see also "Polio") Sterilization Center (Box A6)
      - Surgery/Surgical Instruments (Box A6)
      - Volunteer Services (Box A6)
      - Well Baby Clinic (Box A6)
      - Women's Hospital (Box A6)
      - General Shots (Box A6)
    - Hough, Dr. Paul V.C. (Box A6)
      (see also Phoenix Project)
    - Housing-Typical Rooming House (Box A6)
      (see also Cooperative housing, fraternities, individual residence halls, North Campus, Sororities and Women's Housing)
    - Human biology-Ecological studies (Box A6)
    - Huntley, Prof. Frank L., March 1951 (Box A6)
      (see Student Activities,)
    - Huron River from the Island (Box A6)
    - Hutchins, Harry, former U-M President, 3 negatives (Box A6)
    - Hutzel's department store (Box A6)
  - I-L
    - Ice Research (Box A6)
    - Indians, American, in West Park, 3 negatives (Box A6)
    - Industrial Health and Institute for Industrial Health, 6 negatives (Box A6)
    - Infantile Paralysis Grant (Box A6)
      (see Polio)
    - Inglis House/Estate, 2 negatives (Box A6)
    - Institute for Human Adjustment (Gerontology), 10+ negatives (Box A6)
    - Institute of Human Biology (Box A6)
    - Institute of Public Administration, 9 negatives (Box A6)
    - Institute for Social Research, 7 negatives (Box A6)
      (see also Survey Research Center)
    - Interlochen (Box A6)
      (see National Music Camp)
    - International Center, 8 negatives (Box A7)
    - Investment Officer (Box A7)
    - Japanese Festiva1 1952, 10 negatives (Box A7)
    - Japanese Professor Economics (Box A7)
    - Japanese Studies (Box A7)
      (see Center for Japanese Studies Japanese Ambassador, see Foreign Visitors)
    - Jazz at the Philharmonic (Box A7)